<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The glory and beauty of Gods portion: set forth in a sermon preached before the honourable House of Commons at the publique fast, Iune 26. 1644. / By Gaspar Hickes, Pastour of Lanracke in Cornwall, a member of the Assembly of Divines.</title>
            <author>Hickes, Gaspar, 1605-1677.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 97 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86325</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1838</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E2_10</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2493</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872075</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872075</idno>
            <idno type="VID">124497</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86325)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 124497)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 1:E2[10])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The glory and beauty of Gods portion: set forth in a sermon preached before the honourable House of Commons at the publique fast, Iune 26. 1644. / By Gaspar Hickes, Pastour of Lanracke in Cornwall, a member of the Assembly of Divines.</title>
                  <author>Hickes, Gaspar, 1605-1677.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 43, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G.M. for Christopher Meredith at the Signe of the Crane in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Isaiah XXVIII, 5-6 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:124497:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Glory and Beauty OF GODS PORTION: SET FORTH In a SERMON preached before the Honourable Houſe of COMMONS at the Publique Faſt, <hi>Iune</hi> 26. 1644.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY</hi> GASPAR HICKES, Paſtour of <hi>Lanracke</hi> in <hi>Cornwall,</hi> a Member of the Aſſembly of DIVINES.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>G. M.</hi> for <hi>Chriſtopher Meredith</hi> at the Signe of the Crane in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1644.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="order">
            <pb facs="tcp:124497:2"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Die Mercurii,</hi> 26<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 
                     <hi>Iunii,</hi> 1644.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is this day ordered by the Commons aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in Parliament, That Maſter <hi>Rous,</hi> Maſter <hi>Salwey</hi> and Maſter <hi>Nicoll,</hi> doe from this Houſe give thanks unto Maſter <hi>Hardwick</hi> and Maſter <hi>Hickes</hi> for the great paines they tooke in the Sermons they preached this day, at the intreatie of this Houſe, at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Margarets Weſtminſter,</hi> it being the day of publike Humiliation, and to deſire them to print their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons. And it is ordered that none ſhall preſume to print their Sermons, but whom they ſhall licence under their hands writing.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H. Elſynge Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="appointment">
            <p>I appoint <hi>Christopher Meredith</hi> to print my Sermon, <hi>Gaſp. Hickes.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:124497:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HONOVRABLE HOVSE OF COMMONS now aſſembled in <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is the commendation and glory of great works to be carried through difficulties, to be borne up and brought to paſſe in deſpight of oppoſitions. The <hi>ſtreet &amp; wall</hi> of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> were <hi>built in troublous times.</hi> The Church comonly paſſeth thorough <hi>fire</hi> and <hi>water</hi> to her higheſt advancements &amp; inlargements. So it comes to paſſe, partly thorough the malice of adverſaries, who ſtraine their rage higher according to the Churches riſings; if we could empty hell and the world of enmity, we might perhaps) ſteale quietly to Heaven, and injoy ſpirituall priviledges with out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward eaſe; principally, thorough the wiſdome of God in the diſpenſation of mercies; he raiſes the value of them by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them off upon hard termes. We ſhould be apt to ſurfet of priviledges, to <hi>kick againſt him that feeds us, and light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to eſteeme the rock of our Salvation,</hi> if the Lord did not diet and phyſick us, if he did not acute our appetites by ſome ſharp mixtures, ſome bitter ingredients in our ſweeteſt and fulleſt cup; if he did not keep our ſouls in a longing temper by holding forth bleſsings to us, after which we muſt reach and ſtraine, and preſse even thorow a piece of hell, through a world of dangers and hardſhips before we attain them. And
<pb facs="tcp:124497:3"/>if good things dearly come by are to be highly prized, I do not ſee how we can over-rate thoſe we are now purſuing. All our gold in full weight cannot ſatisfie our enemies, their ſword is cast into the ballance, they hunt after our pretious ſouls. Yea, the Lord cals upon us to expend not only teares and cries, but bloud and life and all: Rich mercies they are which he holds at ſuch a rate, indeed more worth then <hi>our all.</hi> The inſuing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe ſhewes forth a little glimpſe of their excellency, which in all humility I preſent to your view. It is your high pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment in Gods favour <hi>(Honourable Patriots)</hi> that he conveyes our bleſsings to us through your hands that you are made the chieftaines, the leaders among and above your bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren. And although the heat, the brunt lie mainly upon you, yet are your protections ſtrong, your reward ſure. I need not tell you that the eyes of men and Angels are upon you; that the Christian world is at agaze, filled with expectation of the glorious reſults of your high and difficult indeavours. We all riſe or fall, in all probability) as you ſtand faithfull &amp; uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the work you have in hand. Your imployments are emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, your intereſſes deep; the concernment is publike, reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all that have a ſhare in <hi>Zions proſperity.</hi> The Lord <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten you as nailes in a ſure place,</hi> that we may be <hi>an ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation of juſtice, and a mountain of holineſſe,</hi> and the bleſsings of the Lord may be upon us. So prayeth</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your humble Servant in Soul-affaires GASPAR HICKES.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:124497:3"/>
            <head>THE Glory and Beauty OF GODS PORTION.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ISAI. 28.5, 6.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>In that day ſhall the Lord of hosts be for a crowne of glory, and for a diademe of beauty unto the reſidue of his people:</p>
                  <p>And for a ſpirit of judgement to him that ſitteth in judgement, and for ſtrength to them that turne the battell in the gate.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is an evill among all things that are done under the Sunne</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi>) that in reſpect of outward occurrences,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 9.2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>there is one event to all,</hi> to the righteous, and to the wicked; to the cleane, and to the uncleane; to the pious, and to the prophane; whence the hearts of the ſonnes of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:124497:4"/>men are filled with evill, and madneſſe poſſeſſes their mindes till it bring them to deſtruction. That which makes deſperate ones runne mad in ſinning is their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of Gods connivence at their courſes, their damned inference of his approbation of their evils from their preſent impunity and proſpering in them; becauſe they have no changes,<note place="margin">Pſal. 55.19.</note> therefore they feare not God. And that which drives the ſager and better tempered ſort of Naturaliſts out of their wits is their conceit of careleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or confuſion in the diſpenſations of providence, or of unequall compenſations of meedes or puniſhments to men according to deſervings. Hence <hi>Brutus</hi> that wonder of magnanimity and conſtancie, that ſtour ſtickler for the libertie of his countrey, a great admirer and practitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of vertue, and an able aſſertour of the divine provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, ſuch as he knew; when he was finally vanquiſhed by <hi>Antonius,</hi> and ſaw ſuch bad ſucceſſe in his cauſe which he tooke to be ſo good; he diſclaimes all his vertues as trifles, and derides endeavours to live well as vain and bootleſſe. But though reaſon be puzled, yea confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at that which is above its reach, yet faith can fathome theſe depths, and ſo farre ſatisfie its ſelfe in them, as to ſee the Lords hand, and to juſtifie his proceedings. And that which beares up the beleeving heart from faintings or fluctuations amidſt the various and ſtrange viciſſitudes of things below, is the conſideration and aſſurance of an over-ruling and unerring concurrence, diſcerning, dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting, diſpoſing all, in a moſt free, wiſe, and equall courſe, even in thoſe paſſages and exigents which ſeeme to be moſt diſordered or uncertaine. Then when bad men are crown'd with pride, fatted with luxury, mounted on horſe backe in unworthy advancements, whence they
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:124497:4"/>over-look with diſdaine, and trample upon with inſolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie Gods humble, holy, innocent ones: or then when the Lord ariſeth to ſhake the earth terribly, and to worke dreadfull deſolations in the middeſt thereof, he hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes a ſelected parcell, which is his deare charge, to whoſe ſafety and honour he beares tender and unalterable reſpects in the moſt doubtfull or dangerous times.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In that day</hi>] whether it be the ſhort <hi>day</hi> of the wickeds proſperitie, or the determined <hi>day</hi> of vengeance upon them, ſhall <hi>the Lord of hoſts be for a crowne of glory, and for a diademe of beauty,</hi> for trueſt advancement and orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>to the reſidue of his people,</hi> to that pretious portion which is his owne according to the election of grace; <hi>He ſhall be for a ſpirit of judgement to him that ſits in judgement:</hi> He will raiſe up inſtruments, and fit them with faithfulneſſe and activitie for the adminiſtration of Juſtice: <hi>He ſhall be for ſtrength to them that turne the battell in the gate:</hi> He will infuſe courage, and adde wonderfull ſucceſſe to their attempts that fight his bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels, and jeopard their lives for his cauſe.</p>
            <p>The words read unto you are a propheticall Promiſe, let it not ſeeme unſutable to the day for me to handle a Promiſe. It is our worke to day to humble our ſoules and poure them out in prayer; and what ſo proper and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing to melt a gracious ſoule as the goodneſſe of a Promiſe? and where but in the Promiſes ſhall we look for grounds and matter of our requeſts? and what one ſingle Promiſe in Scripture can more directly and fully anſwer our deſires than this? we groane after Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, this Promiſe holds it forth to us in the honourable and amiable notions, of <hi>glory</hi> and <hi>beauty:</hi> Our ſupreme Councell, our Kingdomes Worthies are this day on their
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:124497:5"/>knees before the Lord, and what bleſſing would they beg of God, or we for them rather then the <hi>ſpirit of judgement</hi> here promiſed? Our Armies are in the field, and if we were put to the option to find out and beſeech an advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to them, we cannot bethinke a better than is here ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, that <hi>the Lord would be their ſtrength.</hi> If I had a ſpirit and a tongue to ſet forth, and you hearts rightly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſed to aske what is here contained, I might impart, and you obtaine the fulneſſe of the bleſſing of God.</p>
            <p>That we all may doe our duties the better, I beſeech you looke over the Promiſe againe, wherein you may finde remarkable:
<list>
                  <item>1. The ſeasonableneſſe of it, intimated in the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of time when it ſhall be accompliſhed, <hi>In that day.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. The pretiouſneſſe, expreſſed in the ſubſtance of good things aſſured, the Lord himſelfe undertakes to be <hi>for a crown of glory and for a diademe of beauty,</hi> rich, and ſure, and honourable advantages theſe.</item>
                  <item>3. The peculiaritie of the Priviledges, appropriated they are to Gods <hi>reſidue</hi> or remnant, the perſons with whom alone he ſtipulates.</item>
                  <item>4. The ſpecification of two choice excellencies where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he honours and beautifies his covenant people:
<list>
                        <item>1. <hi>The ſpirit of judgement,</hi> for Civill Government.</item>
                        <item>2. Holy valour and <hi>ſtrength</hi> for military exploits. <hi>In that day,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The parts I ſhall handle in the ſame order as they lie diſpoſed in the Text, beginning with the ſeaſonable ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of this pretious Promiſe ſet downe in the circumſtance of time, of which a word only, becauſe I may not ſpend much of the little time allotted me about a circumſtance.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:124497:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>In that day</hi>] If you conſiderately calculate the time here noted by a view of the context, you will find it to be a time of foule degeneration, when the greateſt part was ſwollen in pride, ſlimed with ſenſualitie, growne to an height of inſolency and univerſality in ſinning, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ripe for a judgement, yea indeed it was the very day of wrath, when deſtruction like a violent ſtorme, a deluge of mighty waters did daſh and overwhelme the flower of their beauty, when like a greedy devourer it conſumed moſt of their viſible ſtrength and excellencie: In ſuch a <hi>day</hi> tis much if the Lord affords ſhelter to his deare ones, an <hi>hiding place till the indignation be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>past:</hi> yet more it is which he here undertakes for them, even then to keepe them up in their honour, to raiſe them higher in happineſſe, when his ſeverity is moſt ſharpe, and his judgements are moſt heavie round about them. 'Tis a cleare truth, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>That in the worſt and moſt dangerous times the Lord doth certainly provide for the glory and the beauty, the advancement and the ornament of his choſen people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you looke for the literall or hiſtoricall accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this truth, you will find it in the bleſſed reignes of <hi>Hezekiah</hi> and <hi>Ioſiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chron. 29. &amp; 34.</note> wherein after the Lord had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved the ten tribes out of his ſight, and cut ſhort Judah for their high provocations, yet ſome glorious reſpites he affords to his remnant, wherein Religion and Juſtice re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered their flouriſh, and the ruined honour of that Church and ſtate revived and got ſtrength. But if you conſider the Promiſe in its generall drift, in its extent or amplitude, as it reaches and belongs to all the faithfull, then might I by a plaine and plentifull induction ſhew how from time to time it hath beene performed: but I ſhall not multiply inſtances, rather I ſhall ſingle out ſome
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:124497:6"/>few that are moſt eminent and remarkable. And where ſhould I begin but at the moſt glorious advantage that ever befell the Church, the ſumme of ſaving Priviledges ſo much deſired, ſo long looked for, to which its proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble this Promiſe mainly points? I meane, the exhibition of Chriſt in the fleſh: upon what times fell that? even upon the moſt degenerate and deplorable that might be: when the <hi>glory of the Scepter was departed, and the beauty of truth and worſhip</hi> fouly blemiſhed and razed, when the Church was even at the loweſt ebbe. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, when Chriſt had gathered a people for himſelfe, and ſuffered Sathan to vent his malice againſt them in bloudy oppoſition, when the rage of perſecutours was at the achme,<note place="margin">Euſeb E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cleſ Hiſtor. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 8 c. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> at the height. When <hi>Diocleſian</hi> and <hi>Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mianus</hi> had vowed the extirpation of the Chriſtian Name, when their ſavage crueltie had more exhauſted the world, then ever any warres had done (as the Hiſtorian ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves) even then on the ſudden doth the Lord chaine up the grand enemie,<note place="margin">Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ius.</note> checke and over-turne his fell agents in their fierceſt careere, and introduce glorious liberty, a flouriſhing calme on his heritage. In ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ages, when the weedes of hereſie ſprang apace in the fat and well manured ſoile of the Church, and at laſt grew together into popery as into one ſtemme, all errours and villanies falling into that as into a common conflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence or ſinke, when that man of ſinne was ſwollen up to ſuch monſtrous inſolencie,<note place="margin">Melchior Adam. in vitâ Lutheri.</note> that he ſet his feet upon the neck of all authority, when he was waxen impudent in blaſphemies, inſomuch that <hi>Tecelius</hi> the foule-mouthed publiſher of his indulgences bluſhed not to affirme that by the Popes power (<hi>interventu pecuniae,</hi> mony he muſt have too) he could pardon him that had defiled the bleſſed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:124497:6"/>the mother of Chriſt; even then did the glorious Sun of truth breake forth in the preaching of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, many Nations threw off the yoke of Antichriſt, and ſubjected themſelves to a beautifull Reformation. But whether doe we wander from our ſelves? what neede we looke for forreigne or farre fetcht inſtances? never was this truth more evidently exemplified in any Nation or Church under Heaven then in ours. When did the Lord advance us to the dignity of his people, and eſtabliſh his truth and worſhip amongſt us in a peaceable and beautifull manner? even immediately after that cloud of bloud which fell in our <hi>Marian</hi> dayes had beſmeared our land, when whoſoever would keep conſcience, and get Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven at laſt, muſt looke to be tranſported thither in a fiery convoy. Why then run thorough all ages, inquire of the former and latter dayes, and you will find that in the ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt and moſt ſinfull times the Lord provides, moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly and gloriouſly for the ſecurity and honour of his people.</p>
            <p>And indeed what fitter opportunities can be found out, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>
               </label> or thought upon, wherein the Lord ſhould magnifie him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in doing great things for his ſervants? For when is his hand ſo viſible and his helpe ſo glorious as in extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities? <hi>It is time for thee Lord to work</hi> (ſaith <hi>David</hi>) <hi>for they have made voide thy law, Pſal.</hi> 119.126. when men have violated all bonds both ſacred and civill, cut in two the ſinewes of the lawes authoritie, and let themſelves looſe to all exorbitancies; high time then for the Lord to take the matter into his owne hand, to ſtirre up himſelfe for the vindication of his honour. A remedie applyed <hi>rebus confuſes &amp; perditis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Calvin in loc.</note> when things ſeeme deſperate and paſt cure, how wonderfull and welcome muſt it needs
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:124497:7"/>be? Then doth the <hi>glory</hi> of a deliverance appeare, when the Almighty hand hath broken thoſe knots and difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, laid open thoſe ſtreights which otherwiſe were alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether inextricable; and then doth the <hi>beauty</hi> of a Church ſhine moſt conſpicuouſly, when ſhe hath recovered her purity, and eſcaped peſtilentiall contagion in bad times, when ſhe is quitted from thoſe blemiſhes that threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to over-ſpread her by a ſeaſonable and thorough Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation. But I have promiſed brevity in this point.</p>
            <p>Let us ſee a little only how the truth will ſute with our times. That perillous dayes were upon us before the flames of publique wrath and miſery brake forth, none will deny, except ſuch as are ſtupid under any miſchiefes, or are actours or abettours of ours. I will not ſo much as mention in what caſe our Lawes and Liberties, Lives and Liberties ſtood. I deſire to limit my ſelfe within mine own verge, and I beleeve men are ſenſible and querulous enough of the evils that touch their skins,<note place="margin">James 2.19.</note> Devils tremble at the ſenſe of miſery, Chriſtians ſhould ſearch out the cauſe, and take that to heart. And if the ſins of men cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt the times and make them dangerous and trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, think ſadly then upon what a generation we are fallen (oh that I might ſay) what diſmall dayes we have eſcaped. For Religion (which is the main) how hath the power of it been denied and cryed down in a deſpight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and furious way of oppoſition, the purity ſophiſtica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and defaced by baſe mixtures, rotten formalities? Oh 'twas enough to cauſe any tender and truly affected ſoul to feel pangs of ſpirit, to hold his loynes, to fall into tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell, and bring forth an <hi>Ichabod,</hi> an iſſue of conſternation, or doubtfull aſtoniſhment, to ſee thoſe uncircumciſed Philiſtines, Popery and prophaneneſs, irreligion and will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worſhip
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:124497:7"/>ſeizing on the <hi>Arke,</hi> and driving away the <hi>glory of the Lord.</hi> For truth how hath it been ſilenced, perver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, mangled? the day would faile me almoſt to reckon up the exploded, monſtrous, licentious errours that have been raked up out of hell publiſhed and patronized among us. For manners, I thinke the Sunne never looked upon a people nor meaſured an age more conſpurcate or corrupt then ours, 'twere eaſier and fitter to bewaile with teares, then expreſſe in words the exceſſive height of our pride and oppreſſion, injuſtice and bloud, luxury and ſenſuality. And as ſinne hold poſſeſſion, ſo did judgement lie at the doore, which hath ſince fallen upon us as a devouring beaſt: how could it be but that ſo much filth muſt ſend up vapours to darken the face of Heaven with indignation againſt us? Oh the dreadfull cloud that ſtill hangs over us, ſhowring downe an horrible tempeſt of wrath! a viall is poured out that turnes all into bloud. Now if at this point the Lord be pleaſed to turne againe the captivitie of our Zion, to cleare up all, and ſhine upon us with favour, what will this be leſſe then a <hi>Reſurrection from death?</hi> how will our <hi>glory and beauty</hi> (as that rare bird) revive from the very aſhes of a ruinous decay? But if as yet we are not brought low enough for ſuch an exaltation, if the times are not yet at the worſt, if ſharper ſeaſons muſt be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, if our preſent hopes ſhould be ſtrangled in the birth, or nipped in the bud, which the Lord avert; here's the comfort, that in ſuch <hi>a day</hi> when the wickedneſſe of the enemies is fully ripe, and Chriſts Spouſe hath ſate long enough in the duſt, when things are brought to ſuch a paſſe that the Lord may be moſt magnified in the confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of inſolent adverſaries, and the advancement of his dejected depreſſed people, even then will he certainly be
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:124497:8"/>
               <hi>for a crown of glory and for a diademe of beauty</hi> unto them, which is the ſecond particular, the high and honourable advantages here promiſed to the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Glory</hi> is the luſtre or ſplendour that reſults from dignity, and <hi>a crown</hi> is the higheſt enſigne of honour, the principall token of Majeſty. <hi>Beauty</hi> is the impreſſion of ſweetneſſe or lovelineſſe, and <hi>a diademe</hi> is the moſt ſtately ornament to ſet forth beauty, and make it more amiable. And a compoſure of <hi>glory</hi> and <hi>beauty</hi> makes up a piece of moſt abſolute and exact ſymmetry, conſiſting of all the parts and lineaments of perfection. To ſuch compleat excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie doth the Lord raiſe his covenant people. In the verſes preceding my Text we find mention of a <hi>crown,</hi> but 'tis the <hi>crowne of pride,</hi> of <hi>glorious beauty,</hi> but 'tis <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding like a flower:</hi> by which the Prophet expreſſes the uſurped domineering of the wicked, which ſhall be troden in the dirt, or (as ſome think) he alludes to their feſtivall garlands, the impudent badges of luxurie and laſciviouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; to which he threatens a terrible blaſt, a ſhamefull withering. And continuing the Allegorie, by the ſame termes uſed in a different ſenſe, he ſets forth the true ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and excellencie of the Godly. The <hi>Lord of hoſts</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe undertakes to be their <hi>glory,</hi> by intereſſing them in all ſublime and ſaving Priviledges, He is their <hi>beauty</hi> by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing on them the ſweet and comely Properties of grace; and in both <hi>crownes</hi> and <hi>diadems</hi> are gifts well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitting the bounty of the higheſt Majeſtie to his beloved Ones: Indeed</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The preſence or the favour of God is the only glorious ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement and ornament of a people or perſon.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label>
            </p>
            <p>What is it elſe that makes the Church an <hi>eternall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 60.15-19.</note> 
               <hi>a joy of generations? Iſai.</hi> 60.15. then doth <hi>ſhe ſucke
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:124497:8"/>the milke of nations, and the breſts of Kings,</hi> when found and eminent members are added to her; <hi>her braſſe becomes gold, her iron ſilver,</hi> when ſhe is ſtored with pretious gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, edified with pure ordinances; <hi>her wals are ſalvation, and her gates praiſe,</hi> when ſhe is guarded externally by good Government; internally by the everlaſting armes, the watchfull eye of Heaven: <hi>her brightneſse</hi> ſurpaſſes <hi>ſunne and moone,</hi> when the direct and unclouded beames of divine favours ſhine upon her, when her <hi>God</hi> is her <hi>glory, verſ.</hi> 19.</p>
            <p>This is the truth, the top of excellencie, if we conſider:
<list>
                  <item>1. Who it is that dignifies and adornes: even the <hi>Lord of ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ts the King of glory,</hi> able to <hi>bring low and to lift up,</hi> who ownes the <hi>pillars</hi> of the <hi>earth,</hi> and hath ſet the world upon them, who in the moſt glorious exerciſe of his Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty <hi>raiſes his poore ones out of the duſt, and ſets them among Princes,</hi> I Sam. 2.7, 8.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>How:</hi> he puts ſome of his owne honour upon them, imparts his owne nature to them, <hi>beautifies</hi> them with his <hi>owne comelineſse, Ezek.</hi> 16.14. for what is true grace but <hi>particula D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i,</hi> ſomething of God, a piece of Heaven?</item>
                  <item>3. What manner of glory and beauty is thus impreſſed, <hi>viz.</hi> that which is ſpirituall and internall, which though it be inviſible and inconſpicuous to carnall view, which can ſee nothing in the Saints, but their burdenſome taske, their heavie preſſures, their bitter incounters, their ſad dejections; yet this ſets majeſtie and ſweetneſſe on the inner man, ſo that under a clouded and calamitous out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide that is full of ſerenity, in a meane and deſpiſed condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that is truly heroique and magnanimous, that wants no worth nor lovelineſſe, though naked of all externall dreſſes and contributions.</item>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:124497:9"/>
                  <item>4. To what purpoſe this is conferred: to wit, that the great God may take up his reſidence, and faſten his deareſt delights on his poore creatures; hereby he workes them to ſutableneſſe, and ſo to communion with himſelfe, who is all glory and beauty; he makes his <hi>ſanctuary glorious,</hi> becauſe tis the <hi>place of his feet,</hi> Iſai. 60.13, where he walkes, and converſes, and diſcovers himſelfe graciouſly: he <hi>clothes the Kings daughter in wrought gold, that he may deſire her beauty,</hi> Pſal. 45.11. that he may impart his heart love, his boſome counſels, his bleſſed imbraces to her as to his Spouſe. Thinke ſeriouſly what a prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it is to be a Favourite of Heaven, in Covenant and Communion with God.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Suffer me here a little more diſtinctly to ſhew how and in what reſpects eſpecially the Lord doth <hi>advance</hi> and <hi>adorne</hi> a Church or people.</p>
            <p n="1">1. This is effected when the ignominious naeves or ſtaines of abuſes are wiped off by Reformation: this is the <hi>repairing of the breaches of Gods houſe,</hi> the purging the body from peccant humours; this is ſweeping the floore, wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the garden, fining the ſilver from its droſſe. And that is <hi>glorious and beautifull</hi> Reformation</p>
            <p n="1">1. Which is hearty; when a people upon deep convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their decayes and degenerations ſet themſelves in earneſt to recover their ſpirituall loſſes: <hi>Turne ye even un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me with all your hearts</hi> (ſaith the Lord, <hi>Ioel</hi> 2.12.) <hi>with faſting weeping, and mourning,</hi> an overly paint of emen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, a neceſſitated laying downe of ſome groſſer evils will be to no purpoſe. There is nothing that ſo much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves communion with God as the eſtranging of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and they will be moſt forward and forcible in recloſing with him, when we get up to a good pitch
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:124497:9"/>of honour and happineſſe in his favour.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Reformation muſt be intire of thorough. 'Twill admit no ſutes for a little <hi>Zoar,</hi> nor ſpare a delicate <hi>Agag</hi> nor keep alive curſed fatlings under pretext of ſacrificing, nor leave the high places ſtanding, becauſe they are faire ſtructures; but it ſtrikes at every evill little and great, plauſible and profitable, that is deſtined and devoted to deſtruction.<note place="margin">Ex peſſimo ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere ne catulus quidem haben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus.</note> When the ſouldiers ſlew <hi>Maximinus</hi> the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and his ſonne, they cryed out, <hi>Keepe not one whelp alive of ſo bad a litter.</hi> 'Tis in vaine to lop off the mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters head except it be feared; miſchiefes attempted and not extirpated will certainly repullulate or multiply;<note place="margin">Quicaquid non eſt peractum, pro non inchoa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt. <hi>Plin.</hi>
               </note> here that ſaying holds true, <hi>Better never to begin then not to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh:</hi> To irritate ill humours and not expell them will increaſe diſtempers in the body, whereas a thorough cure frames it to a more firme habitude of health then ever.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Reformation ſhould be generall and thorough, as in reſpect of parts, ſo of perſons alſo: all of all ſorts ſhould come under it. Materials muſt be prepared before the building can go up; there muſt be hewing and ſquaring, and apting of each part and parcell before the whole can be ſet together in a comely compoſure. We put our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers upon an unreaſonable an impoſſible taske, when we expect and cry upon them for accompliſhment of the worke, and we retard and daſh their endeavours by our unſutableneſſe. Many would have all well in the lumpe, and every thing bettered but themſelves; but how can a handſome ſtructure be made up of rough ſtones and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrought timber? how can a pure Church be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of impure members? aſſure we our ſelves the totall ſumme of Reformation wil amount no higher th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> we find it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:124497:10"/>upon particular accounts, and the onely way to have good times is for every one of us to amend our ſelves.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Lord <hi>dignifies</hi> and <hi>beautifies</hi> a people as by removing corruptions and blemiſhes, ſo alſo by erecting and eſtabliſhing among them the choice Priviledges and Ornaments of his truth, his Worſhip, his Ordinances. The Jewes gloried of their three <hi>crownes,</hi> one of the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> another of the <hi>Prieſthood,</hi> a third of the <hi>Law;</hi> that of the <hi>Law</hi> they preferred, becauſe it regulates and flouriſhes the reſt; and then is that <hi>crown</hi> truly <hi>glorious</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. When it retaines and exerciſes its <hi>ſoveraignty</hi> or pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, when 'tis <hi>glorified</hi> and <hi>prevailes</hi> in mens conſciences. I plead here for Chriſts ſpirituall regiment in the heart by the Scepter of his Word, not for the Pope-like and undue Prelation of perſons, which is not the honour, but the greateſt ſcandall and miſchiefe of a Church: 'Tis a bleſſed and an eternall truth, <hi>The Kingdome of God is not in word but in power,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.20. The majeſty of Chriſts gracious preſence is not perſonated by externall pompe, but declared and magnified by ſpirituall <hi>energy.</hi> Vaine therefore are their feares, and frivolous their objections, who ſuggeſt that a Church looſes all her <hi>glory</hi> when her Miniſters are limited in the exceſſive additionals of earthly honour and aboundance; and I am aſhamed to think that ſo ſordid an argument ſhould be urged by Scholars, whoſe ingenuity (that I name not conſcience) ſhould exceed all others: Oh noble and liberall learning, that ever thou ſhouldſt be proſtituted to ſuch baſe uſes and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects as now thou art! <hi>Bernard</hi> in his dark times com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines of this vile humour in Church-men:<note place="margin">Serm. <hi>10.</hi> ſuper Cantic.</note> 
               <hi>In the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices and dignities of the Church</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>men ſeeke the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancememt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:124497:10"/>of their eſtates, and not the Salvation of ſoules; 'Tis for Biſhoprickes, Archdeaconries, Abbacies, &amp;c. that they beat their breasts in devotion, and their braines in ſtudy; The mockings, ſcourgings, ſpittings, yea the croſſe of Christ, are cast off as diſgracefull burdens, and new faſhioned orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments forged and worne with much bravery; high titles, rich revenues, popular adoration: after theſe they gape greedily, ſtretch largely, climbe ambitiouſly; let ſoules ſinke or ſwimme they care not, ſo they may lift up their heads, and build their nests on high:</hi> and he concludes that herein the <hi>ſpirit of Antichrist was diſcovered even as a noon-day-devill.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Serm.</hi> 33.</note> For thoſe amongſt us that will not follow the ſonne of <hi>leſse</hi> except they may be ſure of <hi>Vineyards and olive-yards,</hi> and may be made <hi>captaines of thouſands, and captaines of hundreds;</hi> that can ſhape their deſignes to no lower a pitch then a lordly dignity, or a fat plurality; that mind the Univerſity and the Miniſtery onely as a ſtirrop to ambition or a ſtale to covetouſneſſe; 'twere well if their aimes were fruſtrated by plucking the prey out of their teeth, that they were diſcouraged, yea rated off from the holy function, wherein there is no hope they ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meane themſelves conſcionably, ſeeing they enter upon it with ſuch impure intentions. And doubt not but when theſe <hi>offae Cerberi</hi> theſe bewitching baites be removed, the Lord will ſtirre up and qualifie better ſpirits for his owne worke. See this in one inſtance only: Thoſe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Reformers of Germany</hi> did not only drive the Popes do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine out of their countrey, but his tyrannicall Prelacie, his whole rabble of full bellied Clergy, whoſe large in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes were all put into the hands of Princes and States: whom I cannot commend for diſpenſing them to right uſes, perhaps their unfaithfulneſſe therein hath been
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:124497:11"/>one provocation to plucke downe the judgements which have ſince ruined them; yet then were their Schooles and Academies moſt frequent and flouriſhing; and I dare challenge any age within the like compaſſe of time and ground (reſerving alwayes due honour to Chriſts Worthies that have ſince abounded) to paralell that in number and eminency of learned men, who did not only vindicate the truth from <hi>Antichristianiſme,</hi> but all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane literature from blind <hi>barbariſme,</hi> wherein it had long lien buried.</p>
            <p>Let me not be miſtaken here, as if I thought there were too much dignity and maintenance for Miniſters amongſt us, if it were duly conferred and diſtributed. We need not imploy our own help ſo to betray our honour; there are two ſorts of engineeres that are now plotting againſt us: Some in a prophane policy would keep us in a ſlaviſh inferiority to themſelves, and therefore they like <hi>Ierobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ams</hi> way beſt, they would chooſe <hi>Prieſts</hi> of the <hi>loweſt of the people,</hi> or make them ſo; theſe hold a baſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, a poore pittance fitteſt for us. Others againe are for an <hi>eleem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſunary ſalary,</hi> that Miniſters being ingaged to their benevolence, they may by the ſame bond be tied to their conceits and errours. But I ſpeake to wiſe Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, who know how to purge peccant-luxuriant humours, without impairing thoſe that are vitall and benigne. And I beſeech you, (the ſearcher of hearts knowes, I plead not for my owne belly, but for your honour, yea the honour of Chriſt whoſe work you have in hand) I beſeech you let it appeare by ſome ſpeedy and cleare courſe that you intend not the diminution or unſettlement of the <hi>double honour</hi> of Chriſts ſervants, but the eſtabliſhment and enlargement thereof.<note place="margin">Iſai. 46.6.</note> Idolaters <hi>laviſh gold out of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:124497:11"/>the bag;</hi> ſuperſtition caſts exceſſe upon its inſtruments; let not Religion ſtarve nor pinch them that wait upon her, let exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitancies be pared away, but let Chriſts due be preſerved, and then I will not doubt to reſume what I had in hand, that his royalty is not advanced by the worldly height and ſtate of his neareſt attendants, his throne is not ſupported by ſuch painted props, his Kingdome is ſpirituall, and his Government moſt full of <hi>glory,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 10.4, 5.</note> when <hi>thoughts are captivated and conſciences awed by the mighty weapons</hi> of his own Ordinances and Diſcipline, when they have <hi>free courſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Theſ. 3.1.</note> 
               <hi>due honour</hi> and kindly workings in the hearts of men.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Truth, Worſhip, Ordinances are <hi>glorious</hi> and <hi>beautifull</hi> when they hold their ſimplicity and purity: Mixtures to theſe are not only ſuperfluous but poyſonous; hiſtrionicall and gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy dreſſes of mens putting on are to theſe as a whoriſh paint to a good complexion, or like that unnaturall burden of haire, worne in pretence of ornament, wheras there is nothing to ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber judgements that can render men more uncomely or ugly. Yet how doe men dote upon mixtures? how have we ſeene the pure ſtreames of truth mudded with humane placites and traditions?<note place="margin">Mat. 15.9. Gal. 1.8.</note> the <hi>Commandements of men</hi> cryed up and obtruded upon the conſcience for <hi>doctrines? another Goſpel</hi> preached and entertained, though vented by perſons of leſſe credit be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond compariſon, then an Apoſtle or an Angel from Heaven<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>accurſed</hi> perſons for their labour. Wanton wits have been la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh in broaching, and ſilly ſoules have been greedy in ſnatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up any errours. Well <hi>the words of the Lord are pure words, as ſilver tried in the furnace, purified ſeven times,</hi> Pſal. 12.6. as tis helliſh chymeſtry for ſublimated wits to extractor caſt out the leaſt ſcruple hereof as refuſe, ſo 'tis damnable impoſture for any cheating compounders to put tinne among this ſilver, droſſe among this pure mettall. The compleat body of <hi>faith</hi> was <hi>once delivered to the Saints, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſimul &amp; ſemel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jude 3.</note> fully and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:124497:12"/>wholly intruſted with them: they that wilfully or remiſſely looſe the leaſt minute thereof hazzard thereby the eternall loſſe of their pretious foules; and they that make or admit the leaſt addition to it, ſhall have <hi>added to them all the plagues written in Gods Book,</hi> Rev. 22.18, 19. no leſſe dangerous are mixtures in point of worſhip, yet doe multitudes run a mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding after them. That good old faſhion of worſhip in Spirit and in truth is cenſured and hiſſed at as a jejune raw humour, or as a fanaticall raſh undertaking; nothing pleaſeth without a pompous outſide, a viſible bravery, though never ſo fond and new-fangled. Yea, have we not ſome who think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as much injured by paring their nailes and polling their haire, as if their hands and heads were cut off? that hold themſelves ſpoiled of the very heart and braine of Religion, if any of their burdenſome and excrementitious ſuperfluities, (the blemiſh and bane of Religion,) be purged out, or lopped off? And no wonder that men are in love with ſuch trifles; they affect a way of worſhip which pleaſes the eye, fils the belly, arrides the ſenſuality. Thoſe <hi>Adiaphorists</hi> or middle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of <hi>Germany</hi> appointed by <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth to compoſe the <hi>Interim,</hi> that monſtrous miſcellany wherewith he thought to pleaſe all parties, did together with ſome ſhreds of truth, ſome patches of Reformation mingle almoſt the whole lum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber or garbage of popiſh rites and ſuperſtitions: amongſt the reſt they would retaine <hi>extreme Vnction;</hi> and it was wittily objected to them that they did it, that they might <hi>ſleeke their owne skinne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t ipſi procede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiores.</note> 
               <hi>and provide for their owne panch.</hi> Queſtionleſſe ſuch a worſhip as breakes no bones, extracts no ſweat from the people, that coſts little paines, and brings in much profit and ſecular advancement to the chiefe actours and upholders of it, ſhall have ſtiffe fautours and abettours every where. But heare what the Lord ſaith of ſuch mixtures to the Prophet, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 43.7, 8, 9. <hi>Son of man, the place of my throne, and the place of,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:124497:12"/>the ſoles of my feet, where I will dwell in the midſt of my people, ſhall not be defiled by their whoredomes, and their carcaſſes, in their ſetting their threſhold by my threſhold, and their posts by my posts, and the wall between me and them:</hi> 'Tis as the filthineſſe of whoredome, as the ſtink of a carcaſſe to the Lord to have hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane inventions erected or interpoſed as parts or props of his worſhip. <hi>Pompey</hi> once in an audacious humour would would needs enter into <hi>the most holy place,</hi> and ſeeing nothing but <hi>a cloud</hi> there, in deriſion he termed the Jewes <hi>Nubicolas, cloud-worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers:</hi> before the Romans thought that <hi>Apis,</hi> or <hi>Iupiter Hamon,</hi> or ſome ſuch ſoule idoll had been incloſed there; how doe men ſeek after and reſt upon the garniſhed outſide, the ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous paint of worſhip, without which they contemne its ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall ſimplicitie as a vaporous or crude conceit? whereas the excellencie, the vigour, the ſoule of it lies in its internall truth, its primitive and native purity.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Lord puts <hi>glory and beauty</hi> upon a people by ſetting up godlineſſe and godly men amongſt them; by increaſing the number, inlarging the graces, advancing the perſons of his Saints and Servants. When the <hi>vileſt men are exalted</hi> the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ruffle and riot at pleaſure, all things are tumultuous and ſqualid, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 12.8. but when the <hi>righteous are up,</hi> there's change of cheere, things are in a joyous and faire ſtate, <hi>Prov.</hi> 29.2. Godly men are the choiſeſt things upon earth,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Cle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Alex.</note> the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, the beauty, the bleſſing of the places that hold them: ſuch ornaments, yea and more glorious are they to the earth, then the <hi>Luminaries</hi> are to the Heavens: and when they are fitly placed in the <hi>Horoſcope</hi> of a Church or State, in <hi>Houſes of Dominion,</hi> oh what an happy aſpect, what a flouriſhing influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence doe they afford. Why then ſhould men of parts and place, perhaps well affected to the publike good, ſtand, aloofe from Religion for feare of contracting diſgrace from it?<note place="margin">Euſeb. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. Hiſt. li. 6. c. 18.</note> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps the devill tels them as <hi>Perph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cy</hi> did <hi>Origen,</hi> that it will
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:124497:13"/>
               <hi>turne their learning into barbariſme, their acuteneſſe into ſottiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> that it will <hi>ſpoile all their gifts and ſufficiencies.</hi> Or elſe he frights them as <hi>Cajetan</hi> did the Electour of Saxony, wiſhing him to beware that he did not <hi>blemiſh his noble houſe by giving credit and countenance to Luther.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caveret ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maculam illuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> aſpergat. <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>len. Adam</hi> in vitâ <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> Profectò inde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ta venit prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propere af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ectatur, periculoſè captatur. <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>za. 2 Chro. 9.21.</hi>
               </note> Satan buzzes it into their eares, that if they favour thoſe frantique fellowes, adhere to thoſe ſtrict truths and wayes, they will ſtaine their bloud, emaſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late their ſpirits, and loſe the garbe and repute of gallants. But harken rather to the Counſels of God, to the Words of truth and ſoberneſſe. To you great ones I ſpeake: Think ſadly how poore, vain, falſe the glory is, that is without God and godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: <hi>truly if you have it tis more then is doe to you, you ſeek it ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and buy it dearely.</hi> Summe up all your ſumptuous ſtore, your birth, breeding, bravery, poſſeſſions, titles, and beſt tis but like <hi>Salomons freight; gold, and ſilver, and Ivory, and apes, and peacocks,</hi> ſtrong mixtures of pride and vanity, enough to poyſon your excellencies, to ſinke your ſhip, to damne your ſouls. Whereas if you ſincerely affect and <hi>honour</hi> Religion, it will <hi>honour</hi> you, yea it will make you the <hi>glory</hi> of your <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>dignity</hi> and <hi>beauty</hi> of your country, otherwiſe the greater you are the more unworthy burdens and blemiſhes you prove to the earth that bears you.</p>
            <p>To bring that which hath been ſaid home to our ſelves, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> I will lay before you only two things by way of information:
<list>
                  <item>1. The <hi>neceſsitie:</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. The <hi>bleſsing</hi> of a preſent Reformation:</item>
               </list> The <hi>neceſsitie</hi> grounded on the <hi>diſhonourable</hi> and <hi>odious</hi> dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations whereinto we were fallen; the bleſſing commended and amplified from the <hi>glorious</hi> and <hi>beautifull</hi> excellencies to which it would advance us.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. The former, the foulneſſe of our decayes and diſtempers I have already touched: and ſo generall they were that they might take up an age of complaining, yea and ſo apparant that you that have your ſenſes about you cannot but ſee and feele
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:124497:13"/>them, though I ſhould ſay nothing of them: Methinks we were even come to that paſſe wherein the ten Tribes lay after their defection: <hi>For a long ſeaſon they were without the true God, without teaching Prieſts, and without Law,</hi> 2 Chro. 15.3. Popery, atheiſme, prophaneneſſe were ſhouldering out our God, our faithfull teachers were cruſhed, ſilenced or diſcouraged, and <hi>Idoll ſheepheards</hi> promoted that ſtarved ſoules, or edified them to damnation; the juſtice and power of our Lawes nullified, force and will carrying all before them. We may gather what ſhould generally have been done, by conſidering what is done where the miſchiefe prevailes. Many dark places of the Land are ſtill the habitations of ſuch cruelties. I ſpeake it in the griefe of my ſoule, the parts to which I ſtand moſt neere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly related are overwhelmed with all the branches and extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of the miſery: and I mention it not to informe you of what you know not, but now in the day of your humiliation (ſeeing the Lord hath made me your remembrancer) to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindle pitty in you and move you to ſpeedy and thorough helpefullneſſe to them. If any miſinformed, or partiall, or an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry fellowes aske us <hi>what ailes us,</hi> when we lift up our eyes, and put forth our endeavours for remedy? Let's anſwer them thus, they would <hi>take away our God, and what have we more?</hi> they would bereave us of our teaching Miniſters, and it would be worſe to want them then to <hi>feede upon the bread of adverſitie and the water of affliction,</hi> Iſa. 30.20. they would ſpoile us of our Lawes, divine and civill, and twere better the Sun ſhould droppe out of Heaven,<note place="margin">Act. 11.28.</note> that our hearts ſhould be torne out of our bodies, then we looſe them. Honourable and beloved, The <hi>Iewes</hi> when they conceived their <hi>Law, and place and Temple,</hi> indangered by <hi>Pauls</hi> preaching, with a joynt and vehement vociferation they cryed out, <hi>Men of Iſrael helpe.</hi> Let me with a better ſpirit and upon better grounds beſpeake you in the name of the Lord, <hi>Men of Iſrael, ye that are Iſrael,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:124497:14"/>Iſraelites indeed, helpe, helpe</hi> every one of you, you by your ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe and authority; you that can doe nothing elſe, by your ſupplications, humiliations, reformations; we by our inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, interceſſions, actions, paſſions; others by their eſtates and lives; every one in Gods way, every one in his own way, help to gaine, to hold theſe things, ſo abſolutely neceſſary: In the day that we let go our holdfaſt, we looſe our <hi>God</hi> and our <hi>good,</hi> our <hi>ſafety,</hi> and our ſubſiſtence, our <hi>glory</hi> and our <hi>beauty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. Take a view of the <hi>bleſsing</hi> of Gods returne to a Church or people; This my Text expreſſes in fulleſt termes, 'tis <hi>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> heightened to a <hi>crowne, beauty</hi> decked with a <hi>diadem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have heard loud bragges of a <hi>glorious ſtate,</hi> a <hi>flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing Church</hi> in our <hi>Land,</hi> and that from the mouthes of them who did what they could to ruine both. Indeed we have had multitudes of eminent Saints brought forth, nouriſhed, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected amongſt us, but no thankes to them, who would not willingly have afforded them a being on the face of the earth, theſe bleſſed Palmes ſprang and ſpread in deſpight of their preſſures. Of late God hath offered in a gracious way to wipe away the <hi>ſtaines</hi> from our <hi>glory,</hi> the <hi>blemiſhes</hi> from our <hi>beauty,</hi> which were many and foule. But how is this mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy entertained? doe men looke upon the wellcome, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire Reformation as the riſing ſun, diſpelling our helliſh darkneſſe? rather they ſtartle and ſtorme at it as a formi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable thing, one ſolicitous for his ill gotten goods, another for ill adminiſtred office, a third for his undue promotion, ſome for their ſelfe opinions, which they will hold to the hazzard of all; moſt for their beloved luſts, which they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre to the glory of God, the ſafety of the State, yea and their own ſoules to: moſt would withdraw their ſhoulder and ſtiffen their necks againſt Chriſt yoke as intollerably rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous; nothing ſo much frights them as the erection and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of an exact diſcipline. Doe men thirſt after the pure
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:124497:14"/>fountaine of truth, the cleere and ſpirituall wayes of worſhip? or rather content themſelves with the <hi>broken ciſternes</hi> of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane inventions, and delight to wallow in the puddles of profaneneſſe and formality? Is it the joy of mens hearts that the <hi>righteous are in authority?</hi> Whence then that grating of ſpirit, that gnaſhing of teeth at their advancement and good ſucceſſe in Gods worke? Men of honour are ſo tender of their reputation, that they will not beare a word of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace without a quarrell, a revenge; and how wary of their beauty are the fondlings of our age? or if they want that which is genuine and proper, they adde paints and ſpots and attires, too often ſuch as are monſtrous and meretricious: yet how wilfully doe men degrade themſelves of the glory to which God would exalt them? how madly doe they teare off the ornaments which he would put upon them? Well though baſe ſpirited, narrow hearted creatures are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuteable and uncapeable of honour, though ſordid clownes neglect and beſmeare their comelineſſe they care not how; yet let us whoſe hearts the Lord hath touched, whoſe eyes he hath opened, prize and purſue theſe bleſſings according to their worth: And if we were but provident, wiſe for our ſelves, we ſhould not account them dearely gained at any rate, no thought it were an age of faſting and prayer, an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of angelicall obedience, the expence of our largeſt liveli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods, our heart blood.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> But alas (ſay many) when ſhall we ſee the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of this promiſe, ſuch <hi>glory and beauty</hi> ſhould be more conſpicuous.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol.</hi> 1. And doe you not ſee the every dayes wonders the Lord is working: 'tis for want of illightned eyes and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full hearts then: could we rightly caſt up our receipts, we might find glorious advantages already upon accompt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Are you offended at the ſeeming ſlowneſſe and diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:124497:15"/>of the progreſſe? 'tis becauſe you miſtake the nature of the worke. One way whereby the Lord commends the worth of his beſt bleſſing to us, is ſometimes our hard com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming by them; The <hi>Iewes</hi> have a tradition, that God ſucked <hi>Moſes</hi> ſoule out of his mouth with a kiſſe, that ſo his diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion might be without all paine: ſuch an eaſie, lazie, good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheape way of reformation doe moſt men affect: they would have all the fatneſſe and ſweetneſſe of Heaven droppe into their mouthes ſleeping; on take heed, wake not the men, fright them not with difficulties, for then they will fling off in diſcontent, or give up all as loſt. 'Tis remarkeable what <hi>Luther</hi> writes to <hi>Spalatinus</hi> touching <hi>Melancthon;</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Epiſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d <hi>Spalat.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Melancthon</hi> was a man of excellent parts, very ſerviceable for Chriſts cauſe; but of a timorous diſpoſition, apt to be overmuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected in difficulties: and at that time extremely penſive he was for feare of ſome ſad iſſues of the great meeting at <hi>Auſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purge:</hi> Whereupon <hi>Luther</hi> wiſhes his friend to exhort and charge him in his name. <hi>Ne fiat Deus, that he make not himſelfe a god,</hi> he might ſeeme to be farre enough from aſpiring to be a god, who was caſt downe below the common pitch of a man. But here was his fault, his projects muſt be like the counſells of God, unerringly and unchangeably ſtand and be effected both in reſpect of time and manner, or the cauſe (he thinks) was loſt, and his ſpirit utterly ſunke. So it is with many amongſt us, they muſt have their own mind and their own will in all things (which is Gods peculiar) or they are undone: If they have not all that they have promiſed or fancied to themſelves, they have nothing at all: If the ſimple <hi>gourde</hi> of their projects of conceits be <hi>ſmitten and wither,</hi> they think <hi>they doe well to be angry,</hi> to be diſconſolate even to the death. But 'tis no diſparagement nor diminution to the worth or comfort of faithfull and bleſſed inſtruments that the Lord over works them, brings to paſſe ſomething, yea the maine
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:124497:15"/>in the moſt glorious undertakings by himſelfe. Have we not ſeene rich bleſſings, eminent atchievements effected by the bare and immediate hand of God, when councels have beene croſſed, endeavours tired, yea hope it ſelfe worne out and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to give up the ghoſt? can we but acknowledge it to be the Lords doing, to bring downe inſolent adverſaries to truth and peace and holineſſe, when they have been trapped and confounded by ſnares of their own ſetting, miſchiefes of their own hatching, who were impregnable by all humane at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts? like to the <hi>Nemean Lion,</hi> which when <hi>Hercules</hi> had ſlaine, he knew not how to get off his skinne, that was ſo hard that nothing could pierce it, neither wood, nor ſtone, nor ſteele; only the Lions own nailes where ſharpe enough to doe it. So hath the Lord turned the pride and madneſſe of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men upon their own heads to their ruine, that otherwiſe were too tough or ſtrong to be dealt with. In great works God will be eminently ſeene and acknowledged, yea, and he carries them thorough inſuperable difficulties and impoſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities to us, that we may ſet him up and truſt in him only.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Why will you diſlike the work for its hardſhip, or tho inſtruments for their ſlackneſſe; and not conſider rather and ſtand amazed at the oppoſition that is made againſt them? I think the devill never played the devill more outragiouſly and apparently then now: all his ſleights and all his furies, and all his confederacies are now on foot: Hell and earth, and Rome openly combined, ſtrongly armed, profeſſedly fighting againſt the honour and happineſſe of our Kingdomes: and ſhall we not have ſomething to doe to fetch our priviledges out of the fire? to winne them at the ſharpes?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Be not too bitter in quarrelling or caſting blame upon oppoſites; but reflect and looke into your own indiſpoſition to the glorious and beautifull work now in hand. Is it a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of nothing think you to reſuſcitate and <hi>animate dry bones,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 37.3</note>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:124497:16"/>to <hi>put fleſh, and finewes, and skinne, and beauty</hi> upon them, to <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe ſpirit</hi> and vigour into them? Indeed the Lord is able to doe it with a breath, with the turne of an hand; yet he uſes to proceed in a wiſe method by little and little, ſtriving as it were with the averſeneſſe of the object. And we ſhall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes find degenerated creatures wofully averſe to Gods rectifying and reforming work. <hi>Iehoſhaphat</hi> ſtretched his ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes, and put forth all his endeavours about the buſineſſe of reformation, but he could not bring to paſſe all he intended, becauſe <hi>the people had not prepared their hearts unto the God of their fathers,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.33. Such crooked pieces, ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tameable monſters doe our reformers find the multitude of men amongſt us. <hi>Hezekiah</hi> made a faire progreſſe in that bleſſed way, and when he had brought things almoſt to the upſhot, the <hi>Priests were too few,</hi> they that ſhould have been moſt forward were unſanctified and unhearty in their duties. Oh the miſerable ſcarcity, the curſed untowardlineſſe we are like to find in our <hi>Sanctuarie men</hi> for the worke of God! 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.34. <hi>Ioſiah</hi> began betimes, and went farre in the beſt paths of his fathers, yet all could not prevent the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwing vengeance to which the guilt and bloud of <hi>Manaſſes</hi> provocations had made the whole obnoxious, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 23.26. now if we lay all theſe and more obſtacles and blocks in the way, 'tis no wonder if the motions of our reformers be ſlow; nay, 'tis well if ever we gaine any ſound recovery, 'tis well if the definitive irreverſible doome be not paſt upon us, and we be not left to confuſion as an incurable people. I ſpeake not this as if I were ignorant or inobſervant of the curſed art of ſome, whoſe drift it is to weare out and bring to nothing the bleſſed work begun by delayes, which they dare not oppoſe by open force, nor yet in favour of their backwardneſſe and benummedneſſe, by whoſe ſlackneſſe it is kept ſo long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the knees, and is in danger of ſtrangling: but only to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:124497:16"/>ſtill and check their impatiencie, who by their precipitous ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtineſſe and fleſhly diſcontent, manifeſt little skill in diſcerning Gods method and manner of working, and leſſe faith in wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting upon his wiſe and gracious diſpenſations under clouds of difficulties and ſeeming protractions, <hi>He that beleeveth maketh not haſte. Iſai.</hi> 28.16.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 'Tis farther objected that we ſeeme to be farre enough from recoveing <hi>glory</hi> and <hi>beauty,</hi> ſeeing the diſhonourable blemiſhes of errours break out ſo much upon us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol.</hi> To this I anſwer, 1. 'Tis not to be denied nor diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, that errours have ſeemed to grow upon us whiles we have been contending for the truth. And we ſhall find more then once that upon the moſt eminent changes in the Church for the better, Satans malice and mens corruptions have caſt in ſuch miſchiefes. <hi>Constantine</hi> the great was the <hi>Angel</hi> that <hi>bound Satan,</hi> the heathen power;<note place="margin">Rev. 12.5.</note> he was that <hi>man-child</hi> at whoſe birth and by whoſe victorie, <hi>the dragon,</hi> the perſecuting Emperours were caſt down and vanquiſhed; yet in his dayes <hi>Arrius</hi> hatched and vented his venome which infected the world. In <hi>Germany</hi> upon the very dawning of reformation the helliſh fogs of <hi>Anabaptiſme</hi> roſe up and flew abroad like <hi>clouds ſpread upon the mountaines.</hi> 'Tis no new thing we ſee for errour to confront the truth moſt petulantly and peremptorily when it is ſpringing up to greateſt purity and luſtre.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This fals not out without ſome advantage to the truth, <hi>There muſt be hereſies</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>that they that are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved may be made manifest,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.19. Many Champions for Chriſt ſhew their valour by incountring and quelling ſuch monſters;<note place="margin">Eph. 4.14.</note> much chaffe is whiffled away by the <hi>blasts of falſe doctrine, and the ſleights of men,</hi> which before lay heaped up with the graine; and many truths are rendred more cleare and glorious, by ventilations and debates with errour.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Do any impute the cauſe and charge the blame of this
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:124497:17"/>evill upon Reformation? why doe they not as well quarrell the Sunne for diſcovering bogs and precipices in their way; or fall out with their Phyſitians for making them the more ſick for the preſent, when they attempt a cure upon their foule bodies? <hi>When I would have healed Iſrael</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>then the iniquitie of Ephraim was diſcovered, and the ſin of Samaria, Hoſ.</hi> 7.1. Many <hi>latent maladies</hi> that have both <hi>root and ſtuffe</hi> in the body ſhew not their apparent <hi>ſymptomes</hi> till remedies be applyed. Ile be bold to affirme that the ſerpentine brood of errours which now crawle abroad were ſpawned in the mud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy times that of late paſſed over us; and how grievous and odious they are to our reformers, Pulpits and Preſſes have in part declared and will doe more by a juſt &amp; full Confutation of them: and I doubt not but authoritie will provide that that ſhall not impudently and impunely exſpatiate, but will uſe its power in a timely and thorough cruſhing of them.</p>
            <p>If there be any yet unſatisfied, either the timerous that ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle at difficulties, or the contentious that cavill at ſome partiall and yet remaining blemiſhes; I muſt plainly tell you, I dare not promiſe you nor my ſelfe ſuch golden dayes wherein no wind ſhall blow, no cloud ſhall riſe: I cannot fancy ſuch an <hi>Idea,</hi> ſuch an exact conſtitution of a Church, wherein there ſhall be no naeve or wrinkle, no diſcraſy or diſtemper. Can the creature here be capable of <hi>glory</hi> that hath no defect or ſtain? of <hi>beauty;</hi> to which there is nothing wanting or redundant?</p>
            <p>Well whoſoever you are that thorough feare, impatiencie, or unreaſonable diſlike of theſe invaluable bleſſings now ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered to us, judge your ſelves unworthy of them, and thruſt them from you; let me tell you that you have <hi>neither part nor lot in this matter.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 8.21. &amp; 13.46.</note> I muſt <hi>turne my ſelfe to them to whom it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs,</hi> for <hi>to them is this Salvation ſent, and they will heare it;</hi> and they are <hi>Gods reſidue. The Lord of hoſts well be,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>to the reſidue of his people.</hi> The third particular, the perſons to whom theſe advantages are appropriated.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:124497:17"/>
            <p>
               <hi>All glorious priviledges,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>all beautifull ornaments belong to Gods ſelected portion, and to that only.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Even to that <hi>choſen generation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.9.</note> 
               <hi>that holy nation, that pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar people,</hi> which the Lord ſingles out for himſelfe in his free and eternall purpoſe,<note place="margin">Mal. 3.17.</note> makes up for his <hi>jewels</hi> by actuall and effectuall calling; hypocrites and formaliſts may partake of generall and externall priviledges, the men of the world have large ſhares of common mercies,<note place="margin">Pſa. 17.14.</note> even their <hi>bellies full of Gods hid treaſures;</hi> but all ſaving favours, yea all favours in a ſaving manner are conferred only on <hi>the remnant.</hi> A man may be hoſpitable and beneficent to his eighbours, gentle to his ſervants, mercifull to his enemies; but his affection and uſage of another ſtraine which he beares and expreſſes to his towardly children, his faithfull ſpouſe, 'tis not for a ſtranger to intermeddle here. Let graceleſſe men prattle of I know not what figment of univerſall grace; let the bond-ſlaves of Satan pride themſelves in the imaginary faculty of their free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will. Our God is infinitely bountifull, but not ſo laviſh as ſome would make him, to caſt away his high honours, his deare delights promiſcuouſly, theſe are the propriety of the elect, the portion of ſons and daughters; theſe are peculiari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed to <hi>Gods reſidue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quest.</hi> But who are this <hi>reſidue?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> I cannot ſtay upon a diſcovery of them. Briefly take notice of them thus,
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Negative,</hi> by their diſtinction. They are not men of the multitude nor of the world, nor of the times; they dare not ſinne of the faſhion, not goe to hell for company; their care is to be at a reall and wide difference from all ungodly and unſound ones; to <hi>be ſaved from the untoward generation.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Act. 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>0.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Poſitive,</hi> by their qualification.<note place="margin">Jer. 2.3.</note> They are <hi>holineſſe to the Lord, the firſt fruits of his increaſe,</hi> prime parcels intirely dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated and vowed to his ſervice, conſecrated veſſels of the beſt
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:124497:18"/>mettall and making, new framed by Gods bleſſed workman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in the moſt delicate artifice of grace,<note place="margin">Eph. 2.10.</note> 
                     <hi>created in Chriſt Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> caſt into his mould, and ſo prepared for honourable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>1.</note> made <hi>meet for the masters uſe.</hi> Their holineſſe is hearty, their maine drift the honour and ſervice of their God.</item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Collectivè,</hi> by their conſociation. They all live by the ſame Spirit, walk by the ſame rule, mind the ſame Heaven, and therefore they are <hi>of one heart, and of one ſoule.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Act. 4.32.</note> Pearles are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted more pretious and fitter for ornament, when they are of equall bigneſſe or ſorted into <hi>Vnions:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> Plato</note> 
                     <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Diamonds</hi> (ſaid the Naturaliſt) <hi>are nothing in price or luster to the conſent of good minds.</hi> And although there may be ſome petty diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between them in judgement, ſome ſmall and tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry diſtance or interruption in affection; yet they accord in the maine, they are ſhaken together in times of triall and ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and as Chriſts cauſe and their owne greateſt good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, they ſtrengthen their union by all warrantable and worthy wayes of mutuall ingagement and helpfulneſſe.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſe</hi> 1. This may ſhew us then that when the Lord doth great works and conferreth great bleſſings he diſtinguiſheth and ſelecteth both inſtruments and objects. Times of the Churches exaltation are times of wideſt and moſt thorough diſtinction. Multitudes would preſſe in for a ſhare of her pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, when ſhe is riſing, that muſt be ſhaken off as burdens and blemiſhes before ſhe can recover her honour. When fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable edicts were publiſhed for the Jewes, their adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries claime acquaintance with them and offer them aſſiſtance, they would needs have a finger in the <hi>temple-work:</hi> but their help is refuſed, and their officiouſneſſe ſuſpected as more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous then their profeſſed oppoſition, <hi>Ezra</hi> 4.1, 2, 3. If there be a <hi>Iudas</hi> among the twelve he muſt be uncaſed before Chriſt have finiſhed his work<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and what have devils to doe to fit in the aſſembly of the Gods? devils in treachery, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:124497:18"/>in impuritie: The mixed multitude, the mungrell crew that came up with the Iſraelites out of Egypt, were touched with a ſtupid admiration of the wonders which God wrought for his people, and promiſed themſelves much hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe in their company; but when they met with ſtreights and wants, and found not things anſwerable to their ſenſuall humour, then they fell a murmuring and a luſting; and the Lord ſwept them away in his diſpleaſure, ſo that none of them reached Canaan, <hi>Numb.</hi> 11.4. One great cauſe of the ſtreights and miſeries that have befallen us in our paſſage from Egypt to Canaan hath been the diſcovery and diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe looſe rotten adherents to Gods cauſe and people. And oh that they were all ſhaken off, while they are unſound at heart, we may take more comfort in their falling away then in their acceſſe. If yet <hi>a ſword pierce deeper into Chriſts ſoule,</hi> if heavier things befall his members, it is that the thoughts of many more <hi>hearts may be revealed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 2.35.</note> that a clearer and more thorough difference may be put betweene the pretious and the vile.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Hath the Lord a <hi>ſpeciall pretious portion</hi> (ſuch as we have heard decyphered) upon which he heapes ſuch <hi>honour,</hi> faſtens ſuch favour, impreſſes ſuch <hi>beauty?</hi> Fearfull it is then, that it ſhould be the butt of mens oppoſition,<note place="margin">Act. 28.22</note> the <hi>ſect-every where ſpoken against,</hi> in common account the <hi>vile refuſe</hi> rather then the <hi>glorious reſidue.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hiſtor. <hi>of</hi> France.</note> The <hi>Marſhall Biron</hi> of <hi>France</hi> was a man impudently and inſatiably ambitious, yet above all his titles of honour he affected to be ſtiled the ſcourge of the <hi>Huguenots.</hi> And how have men of power and policy thought no founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſure enough for their ſecurity, their glory, their content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but that which is laid on the ruines of the eſtates or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of Gods pretious ones? Oh the deepe and curſed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinations or contrivances that have been plotted and urged <hi>to caſt them downe from their excellency,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 62.4.</note> to root them out from
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:124497:19"/>having a name under Heaven, to embitter their beings to them, to make them crouch under unreaſonable and impious burdens. When the <hi>Arrian Biſhops</hi> ſwayed in the Church under <hi>Valens</hi> an <hi>Emperour</hi> of their <hi>hereſie;</hi> Liberty was given to <hi>Iewes, heathens, hereticall Chriſtians</hi> of all ſorts to exerciſe their Idolatry, falſe worſhip, mad feſtivals, what not? only the Orthodox were expelled their Churches: and in one place being aſſembled for holy performances at the foot of a mountaine, under the injury of all weathers, they were thence driven by force of ſouldiers, <hi>Theod. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>ca.</hi> 24. Is it not lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table that in the repute of many amongſt us, Papiſts, Atheiſts, Monopoliſts, ſenſualiſts, drunkards, any the baſeſt ſociety or ſort of men ſhould be held more tolerable then the holy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therhood, the members of Chriſt, the Saints of the moſt High, who alone are deare to God, and linked together in the only gracious and bleſſed Communion? How many for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience and quietneſſe ſake in the raigne of our Prelates did leave their deare countrey, their rightfull poſſeſſions? yet there are not wanting ſome that maligne a wilderneſſe to them. 'Tis a common wiſh, Oh that we were ridde of them all! and why are you greedy of your own ruine? <hi>Should not the Lord of hoſts leave his remnant</hi> among you, ye would ſoone be turned into a <hi>Sodome, Iſai.</hi> 1.9. Their preſence and prayers are the pillars of a Kingdomes ſafety, the procurers of its hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe. And if malice hath not utterly blinded men, let them rub their eyes and ſee two choice excellencies amongſt many here annexed to them and thoſe moſt profitable for humane ſocietie; even <hi>the ſpirit of judgement,</hi> for Civill Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and holy valour and <hi>ſtrength</hi> for militarie exploits: for ſo it followes, <hi>The Lord will be for a ſpirit of judgement to him that, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt of the firſt, the <hi>ſpirit of judgement,</hi> which is the gift of governing well, faithfulneſſ &amp; ability in executing juſtice.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:124497:19"/>
            <p> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>The Lord doth highly dignifie and bleſſe a people by ſetting over them religious and righteous Magistrates and Rulers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis a good argument of Gods favour to Iſrael which <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram</hi> deduces from the choice and qualification of <hi>Solomon: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Lord loved his people, he hath placed ſuch a King over them,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 2.11. And when the Lord undertakes the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and happy reparation of that ſtate after an wofull decay, he promiſeth <hi>to restore their Iudges as at the firſt, and their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours as at the beginning,</hi> to reduce them to primitive purity and integrity, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 1.26. This bleſſing will ſhine the more by ſetting againſt it the miſery and miſchiefe of its oppoſite in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice. <hi>As a roaring lion and a ranging beare, ſuch an one is a wicked ruler over a poore people, Prov.</hi> 28.15.<note place="margin">Cedren.</note> In the dayes of <hi>Phocas</hi> that bloudy uſurper, (he was the firſt ſworn ſlave to Antichriſt that wore a crown) a holy Monk was ſo bold as to expoſtulate or enter diſpute with God: he asked him why he had ſet ſuch an impious wretch over Chriſtians; and he was anſwered by a voice from Heaven (if you will beleeve the ſtory, 'tis related by <hi>Cedrenus</hi>) becauſe a worſe could not be found, and the ſins of men deſerved ſuch a miſchiefe. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates are either the common good, or the common evill of them to whom they have relation.<note place="margin">In Epiſt. ad Spalat.</note> That paſſage of <hi>Luther</hi> is memorable: he was in great danger of death, and he wiſhes that the Pope and his crew might be the only inſtruments of it, he would not have <hi>Caeſar</hi> involved in the cauſe, he would not have his royall hands ſtained with his bloud: for (ſaith he) I know how it fared with <hi>Sigiſmund</hi> after the burning of <hi>Huſs,</hi> nothing proſpered with him, beſides his domeſtique infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies and calamities, the weale-publique ſuffered exceedingly with him and under him. The moſt exemplary judgements are upon the moſt eminent perſons, yea; and they fall not alone, the <hi>poore ſheep</hi> ſmart for their dotages and delinquen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies: whereas the Magiſtrates vertues are the peoples bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:124497:20"/>
               <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10.17. and their vertues are comprized under this expreſſion, <hi>The ſpirit of judgement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quest.</hi> But what is this <hi>ſpirit of judgement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> 1. It is a <hi>renewed ſanctified faculty,</hi> ſaith <hi>David</hi> with ſome of his laſt words that ſavour moſt ſtrongly of Heaven: <hi>He that ruleth ever men, muſt be just, ruling in the feare of God,</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.3. 'Tis true there are functionall abilities inlarged to men, which are profitable to others though not ſaving to themſelves. You may be deep Statiſts, learned Lawyers, exact in the diſquiſition of truth, the deciding cauſes, &amp;c. yet all this doth not amount to the bleſſed property in my Text. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, experience, ingenuity, morall honeſty, nobleneſſe of mind may make men dexterous in the <hi>art of judging,</hi> the Lord infuſes the <hi>ſpirit,</hi> and that ſeaſons all with ſupernaturall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency. Plainly he is a good Ruler indeed that is a gracious Chriſtian to.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>ſpirit of judgement is regular;</hi> as it is framed by Gods finger, ſo tis guided by Gods rule. We explode the Popes <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non law,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luther. Ridiculum planè eſt Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um. Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratorem aeternum nominare, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>om. Eccleſ Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor. lib. 4. cap. 16. V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Itali vultis ha here Deum in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ane, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> non creditu eſſe Deum in calis.</note> and that juſtly, the ſumme whereof is this. <hi>The Pope is god on earth, above all things heavenly, earthly, ſpirituall, ſecular, he hath the propriety of all things, and no man must dare to ſay to him, what doſt thou?</hi> This we diſlike not only becauſe 'tis the Popes, but becauſe 'tis moſt laviſhly irregular, making up a modell of government fitter for <hi>old Perſians,</hi> or moderne <hi>Iurks</hi> then for Chriſts freed men. Strange then it is that men of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, that would be called Divines, ſhould ſo much cry up the <hi>Law</hi> of the <hi>will. Athanaſius</hi> held it abſurd and ridiculous in the Arrians at the Councell of <hi>Ariwinum</hi> to prefixe this title to their forme of Faith. <hi>Praeſente Conſtantio <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>crno, magno</hi> &amp;c. to give the ſtile of <hi>eternall</hi> to the Emperour, and yet to deny the <hi>eternity</hi> of the <hi>Son of God.</hi> And very acute is that of <hi>Melancton</hi> diſputing about the <hi>Euchariſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: You Italians will needs have God to be in the bread, when you doe not, beleeve that there is a God
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:124497:20"/>in Heaven.</hi> And are not they worthier of deriſion then confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, who make men omnipotent and abſolute, and yet ſpoil God of his freedome in decreeing and working, raze or abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate his perpetuall commands, yea and live as if there were no God in Heaven? Let mortals tremble to imitate the thunder of the Almightie by the ſtormes of their exorbitant luſts and paſſions; to take abſoluteneſſe upon them, which is the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicable prerogative of him whoſe throne is in the Heavens.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>ſpirit of judgement</hi> is active. The ſpirit we know is the vigorous principle of motion and action; contrary here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto is that diſtemper mentioned, <hi>Hab.</hi> 1.4. <hi>The Law is ſlacked, defluit lex,</hi> 'tis fallen into a ſwoune: The <hi>Metaphor</hi> is taken from the ſlow, yea, imperceptible motion of the pulſe in the failing of ſpirits. And alas for us for want of activity! we have expected, deſired, magnified, bleſſed, faſted and prayed for a <hi>Parliament;</hi> and we know how much time, ſubſtance, parts, ſpirits, bloud our Worthies have expended for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like good: what dangers and difficulties they have incountred: heretofore and now they have framed for us the beſt Lawes humane under Heaven. Would it not be a ſad thing if this wonderfull power when it comes to execution ſhould be put into paralyticall hands, either quite benummed, or ſo ſhaking, that they can doe nothing evenly or ſteddily? that it ſhould be like a gunne in the keeping of an <hi>Indian,</hi> a rare and forcible Engine in its ſelfe, but made uſeleſſe for want of good mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging? Oh that ever there ſhould be any advanced to place and armed with authority, who thorough the vile timorouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his own ſpirit, or the treacherous compliancy of his owne evill heart with ſin or the times, ſhould not dare to act that good for which he is ſure to have aſſiſtance and accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the moſt High, without the conſcionable perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance whereof he can never ſtand acquitted before the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:124497:21"/>Tribunall! Upon whomſoever the <hi>ſpirit of judgement</hi> which is the <hi>Spirit of the Lord</hi> hath fallen, let them <hi>goe in this their might,</hi> let them put forth their ſtrength, and exerciſe their facultie, the Lord cals and ſends them, and will do great things by them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>The ſpirit of judgement is impartiall.</hi> As the ſoule in the body it diffuſes it ſelf in a juſt proportion thorough the whole into each part according to its ſeverall need and capability. Who ſo ſmall or inconſiderable, who ſo high or uncontrole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able as to be without it influence or reach? by it rulers muſt governe, by it the governed muſt be ruled. The Lord gives a charge and preſcribes a method to the executioners of his ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 9.5, 6. he commands them to ſtrike home, and <hi>to ſpare none that bore not his owne caracter or marke, and to begin at his Sanctuary at the ancient men before the houſe.</hi> Twas the Popes old trick to exempt his <hi>Clergy</hi> from the <hi>Civill,</hi> which detra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctingly he cals the <hi>Secular power:</hi> but the Popes patronage now I hope will nothing help our bad Miniſters. Oh that they might feele the moſt ſpeedy and heavy hand of juſtice, as they have had the deepeſt hand in occaſioning our decay and miſery. <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth was wont to ſay wittily, <hi>If the ſhavelings had been good,<note place="margin">Si Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culi frugi eſſent, non indige<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ent Luthere.</note> there had been no need of Luther.</hi> Let the guilty hang the head, they that are faithfull and conſcionable need not feare nor decline the deciſions of a <hi>Parliament;</hi> the cenſures of righteous Magiſtrates. If any ſay that I ſeek the ruine and publiſh the ſhame of men of mine own calling: I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer no: they are the proud, the perſecuting, the prophane, the popiſh, the temporizing, the inſufficient, the lazy, the drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, the ſcandalous Prelates and Miniſters that diſgrace the holy function, and make us aſham'd of them, as Gentlemen are of their beggarly kinred, or rather as an honeſt man is to ſee his brother goe to the gallowes. And as they have troubled our Iſrael, ſo let the Lord trouble them: Let their <hi>owne dung be
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:124497:21"/>ſpread upon their own faces,</hi> but let Gods Sanctuary be purged of them. Moreover, why ſhould the <hi>ſpirit of judgement</hi> ſhrinke or be abaſhed at the ſtout looks of any overgrowne great one,<note place="margin">Criminoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pa eſt, ubi honeſtior ſtatus. Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vian, li. q. de. Guber. Dei</note> any bluſtring <hi>Belialist?</hi> let ſuch feele the force, the omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency of juſtice. 'Tis a true ſaying, <hi>The higher the condition of the ſinner, the baſer alwayes is the ſin.</hi> What! <hi>will men ſteale, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, oppreſſe, commit adultery ſweare</hi> falſely or blaſphemouſly, drinke drunke, live diſſolutely and debauchedly, and thinke <hi>they are delivered to doe theſe abominations,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 7.9, 10.</note> becauſe they are great in the world? Methinks noble ſpirits ſhould hold it more baſe to deſerve then to ſuffer ſharpe and ſhamefull pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties of juſt lawes which they breake. If you improve your greatneſſe to quit your ſelves from them; your priviledge is no other then theirs, who run mad unchained, and poſt to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition without controll.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>The ſpirit of judgement is uniforme.</hi> It caſts mens minds, and aimes, and actions into one mould or faſhion.<note place="margin">Jam. 4.5.</note> 
               <hi>The ſpirit that is in the world luſteth to envie,</hi> a diſtorting, diſtracting evil. Corrupt men differ as much in minds as faces, or if they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord they meet only in evill. Great ſpirits are lyable to great impulſions, violent concuſſions; when they are whirled by <hi>excentrique paſsions,</hi> or wheeled by byaſſed and ſelfe reſpects, their motions muſt needs be diſordered and turbulent. But when this bleſſed principle in my text is the <hi>Primum mobile</hi> the firſt mover, then all the <hi>ſpheares,</hi> whether ſuperior or infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior in place, ſwifter or ſlower in motion, hold on their owne courſe evenly and conſtantly, and accord with others in an exact correſpondence; and the harmony is really by farre more ſweet, then the imaginary muſique of the heavens was fained to be. <hi>There are diverſities of gifts,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.4, 5, 7.</note> and differences of adminiſtrations, but one and the ſame ſpirit, and the manifeſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that ſpirit is given to every man to profit withall:</hi> all tends to mutuall helpfulneſſe, to the common good of all, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:124497:22"/>one that partake of that Spirit: hence all gifts become ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable and contributary each to other: and 'tis a moſt bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and beneficiall intercourſe or trade that paſſes betweene ſanctified abilities. It hath ever been a rich bleſſing to good Magiſtrates to be inſtructed and abetted in their moſt glorious acts by faithfull Miniſters. <hi>David</hi> had his <hi>Seers,</hi> ſo had <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Aſa</hi> his <hi>Azariah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 15.1. &amp; 19.2. 2 Ki. 19.2. &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2.14.</note> 
               <hi>Iehoſhaphat</hi> his <hi>Iehu,</hi> beſides a number of <hi>teaching Prieſts and Levites,</hi> whoſe Catalogue we find re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtred, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 17.7, 8. <hi>Hezekiah</hi> had his <hi>Iſaiah, Ioſiah</hi> his <hi>Huldah, Zorobabel</hi> his <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> the Elders of the Jewes brought out of captivitie to reedifie the City and Temple, <hi>built and proſpered thorough the prophecying of Haggai and Zachariah the ſonne of Iddo. Temple-work, Church-work</hi> never goes up with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſuch hands. I ſhould be ſorry that any here preſent ſhould judge the Prophets uſeleſſe, or burdenſome, or intermedling without their verge in weighty holy affaires. A Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on pretended without the Councell and Conſociation of men of God would be like <hi>Adonijahs</hi> feaſt,<note place="margin">1 King. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 9, 10.</note> to which <hi>Abiathar</hi> the temporizing Prieſt, and bloudy <hi>Ioab,</hi> and other ſuch like were called, Courtiers (perhaps) and Souldiers, and Politicians enough, but faithfull <hi>Zadok</hi> and <hi>Nathan</hi> the Prophet, and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> the Kings ſon, and true-hearted <hi>Benaiah</hi> being left out, the meeting proved both ſinfull and ſad, it began in conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and ended-in confuſion. But oh happy meetings-where all ſorts of gifts are met together and joyntly improved to mutuall and publique good! 'Tis the good Spirit of God that joynes and keeps men unanimous in and for that with good: and whatſoever tends to the ſetting of good men or good gifts at oddes, though it be never ſo covertly or ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly carried, ſuſpect it as proceeding from the envious one, the evill ſpirit of confuſion.</p>
            <p>I need not adde any thing for application of this point. 'Tis <hi>the ſpirit of judgement</hi> (which hath been deſcribed) that fits
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:124497:22"/>every man for the weighty affaires of Civill Adminiſtration, that is intruſted and imployed in the ſame. You ſee hence <hi>(Noble Patriots)</hi> what it is that you ſhould mainly ſtrive for and cheriſh in your ſelves; and we find what we ſhould moſt importunately beg for you of Heaven. The work before you is glorious, the power in your hands ordinate, the way of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſing it the beſt in the world, moſt ſutable to equity and to our ſpirits; wherein as juſt Soveraignty is not bounded un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily, ſo community hath ſome ſtroke according to its ranke in matters of higheſt publique concernment. Oh then let this <hi>ſpirit of judgement</hi> animate and ſway all your conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and proceedings; let it ſeaſon them with ſanctitie, order them with regularity, manage them with activity, carry them thorough with impartiality, corroborate and crowne them with unanimity; and the iſſue will be (if it be not cut off by ſinfulneſſe and ingratitude) a heape of bleſſings upon us, and upon many generations.</p>
            <p>So much of the <hi>ſpirit of judgement,</hi> the firſt excellency here ſpecified.</p>
            <p>The ſecond followes, which is <hi>ſtrength to order the battell in the gate,</hi> valour and abilities for the warre.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is a choice gift or bleſsing of God,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>the honour and ornament of a State or people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A uſefull ſeaſonable ſubject had I time to proſecute it. I ſhall now handle it very briefly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Lord is a man of war. Exod.</hi> 15.3. and he makes ſome of his ſervants brave warriours; <hi>he girds them with ſtrength,</hi> teacheth them the uſe of their armes, covers them with the <hi>ſhield of Salvation,</hi> gives them undauntedneſſe to encounter, and ſwiftneſſe to <hi>purſuit their enemies,</hi> Pſal. 18.32-40. till they have their necks under their feet.</p>
            <p>Such were the Iſraelites under <hi>Ioſhua's</hi> command, nothing could ſtand before them. Such were the Judges, men won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:124497:23"/>inſpired and inabled to reſcue Gods people from op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion;<note place="margin">2 Sam. 23.8.</note> ſuch <hi>Worthies</hi> had <hi>David,</hi> who was called and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified to cut ſhort the enemies of God, and to erect his Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in purity and peaceableneſſe; and with this bleſſing hath the Lord honoured pious Princes and States, whom he hath ſet up and eſtabliſhed in all ages.</p>
            <p>This holy valour will appeare a choice honourable bleſſing if we conſider it,
<list>
                  <item>1. In the habite. <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>
                     </label> There is naturall hardineſſe in bruits, for which we admire them; morall fortitude in meere men, which renders them both dreaded and renowned; but this is a ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified ſublime gift of the Spirit, an admirable adorning grace.</item>
                  <item>2. In the exerciſe. Fit it is to be imployed in great matters, high exploits, the maintenance of Gods cauſe and truth, the vindication of his honour, the reliefe of his Saints, It ingages ſtrength and life, and all upon ſuch noble deſignes and ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Unholy courage makes men more able to do hurt, it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generates into rage, becomes luſts champion, and breakes out into injuriouſneſſe, revenge, murther, &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>3. In the Uſefulneſſe of it. Mans ſin filled the world with <hi>Antipathies,</hi> and enmities, and God hath armed many of the irrationall creatures to make defence and oppoſition againſt their <hi>Antipathists.</hi> And who have ſo many implacable fierce enemies as the Saints? as they have <hi>need of patience</hi> to beare their injuries, ſo valour is very uſefull and advantageous to repell them, when they find a warrant or call?</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſe</hi> 1. Miſerable then and ruinating to a ſtate is the want of this gift, this bleſſing. And would you know what it is that melts the ſpirits, diſſolves the nerves, enfeebles the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood and magnanimity of a nation? let me preſent it to your view in a home preſident, even of the generations that have paſſed over us, the people that have formerly poſſeſſed our places. The <hi>Brittaines</hi> the ancient inhabitants of this land
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:124497:23"/>were a warlike nation, the made ſtout reſiſtance againſt the Romans, bore their yoke with much reluctancie, and threw it off upon all occaſions:<note place="margin">Engliſh Chronic.</note> yet when their <hi>Nobles degenerated into luſt, luxury, and cruelty; when falſhood and faithleſneſſe both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God and man abounded in all ſorts, when plenty brought forth the curſed fruits of looſe and wanton living: when they were gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally addicted to hate of truth and love of lying, inſomuch that if any were gentler and more given to truth then other, the reſt would worke him all the hurt and ſpight they could; and this did not only the ſeculars, but alſo the Clergie, and the heads thereof, giving themſelves over to drunkenneſſe, pride, contention, envie, &amp;c. ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting from them the yoke of Chriſt</hi> (they are the very words of our ſtory) then they became a ſpectacle of reproach and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, a prey to barbarous nations.<note place="margin">Gens Saxonum ſera. <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vian.</hi>
               </note> The Saxons that ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them were the <hi>Imps of Mars,</hi> a terrour to this part of the world, they lived by their ſword and were victorious almoſt whitherſoever they went: yet when they <hi>grew cold and heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe in the Religion which they had zealouſly profeſſed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Engliſh Chronic.</note> 
               <hi>when trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery, injuſtice, ſhedding innocent bloud, impiety, ſenſuality did overſpread them,</hi> they were wofully waſted by inteſtine broiles and forreigne incurſions, and at laſt ſwallowed up by the <hi>Norman Conquest.</hi> The application of theſe hiſtories <hi>be to the enemies of God,</hi> and of his people. Sins, ſuch ſins as theſe wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken mens ſinewes, emaſculate their ſpirits, devoure their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie, and <hi>cauſe the hearts of the valiant utterly to melt.</hi> Cowardice and baſeneſſe are the proper and certaine effects of ſin. And although wicked men may be ſtout and ſturdy, and mighty to do miſchiefe, either for the ſcourging of Gods people, or the breaking each other in pieces; yet is this in them but beſtiall helliſh fury, no true valour; and the more directly and impetuouſly it is ſet againſt God and goodneſſe, the ſooner and more fatally ſhall it bring themſelves to ruine.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This gives us great occaſion to magnifie the Lord for
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:124497:24"/>this choice honourable bleſſing conferred upon us. <hi>Our bow hath of late recovered its ſtrength:</hi> God hath ſtirred up and fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted courageous ſpirits, excellent inſtruments for military af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires. And although the nature of the warre amongſt us be calamitous, and many events of it very ſad; yet the maine comfort is, the quarrell is apparently betwixt <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt,</hi> he that ſees not ſo much now is wilfully maliciouſly blind. Now the prophecies in the <hi>Revelation</hi> ſeeme to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhew that the ruine of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> ſhall in a good part be brought to paſſe by the <hi>ſword:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev 16 6. &amp; 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.14, 15, 16,17.</note> 
               <hi>They that gave their king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes to the beaſt ſhall recover them by force, they ſhall hate the whore, make her deſolate and naked, eate her fleſh, and burne her with fire. They that make warre with the Lambe, ſhed the bloud of Saints and Prophets, they ſhall have bloud given them to drinke, as they are worthy:</hi> Methinks the Lord is breeding and apting a generation of men amongſt us that ſhall make the <hi>throne of the beaſt</hi> ſhake. If any cenſure me for cheriſhing and blowing up the ſparkes of valour in mens ſpirits,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.3.</note> 
               <hi>With me it is a very ſmall thing to be judged of them, or of mans judgement.</hi> LUTHER was called <hi>a Trumpet of ſedition;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionis.</note> they ſaid of BEZA when he accompanied the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> forces in <hi>France</hi> fighting for their Religion,<note place="margin">Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um flam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> that he <hi>preached a Goſpel compoſed of fire and brimſtone.</hi> But we that are Miniſters need not feare nor ſhame to carry the <hi>Trumpets of the Sanctuary before the Lords armies.</hi> All yee whoſe hearts the Lord hath touched <hi>Goe on in this your might,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Judg. 6.14 Joſh. 1.7. Iſai. 26.4</note> 
               <hi>be ſtrong and of a good courage, be not afraid nor diſmayed, for the Lord your God is with you whitherſoever ye goe in his way, Iehovah who is everlasting ſtrength, is ſtrength</hi> in an eminent glorious manner <hi>to them that turne the battell in the gate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let me cloſe your thoughts with one briefe conſideration from the whole. In all that hath been ſaid you ſee verified that <hi>great Poſition</hi> of the Apoſtle (indeed a <hi>Paradox</hi> to the world) <hi>That Godlineſſe is profitable for all things.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.8</note> Perhaps you
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:124497:24"/>have accounted it needfull and helpfull for the worſhip of God, the ordering of the converſation, Peace of Conſcience, &amp;c. Yet further take notice here how it conduces to the flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing and good government of a ſtate, to the managing and bleſſing of all affaires, not Religion only, but civill and milita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to. 'Tis the feare, the favour, the gracious preſence of God that <hi>crown</hi> a people with moſt <hi>glorious advantages,</hi> that <hi>adorne</hi> them with moſt <hi>precious priviledges,</hi> that proſper them both in <hi>peace and warre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As therefore we tender and deſire the ſafety and honour of our ſtate, the publike and mutuall welfare of Rulers and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, the good and glorious ſucceſſe of our greateſt deſignes; let all of us together, and every one of us in our ſtations, with our heartieſt intentions and indeavours doe what we may to get and keep the Lord amongſt us in the power and purity of Religion. Let this be practiſed, promoted, prayed for above all by all. So will it <hi>dignifie and beautifie</hi> us with all <hi>honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> and <hi>amiable excellencies;</hi> it will burniſh the crown and ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh the throne; it will enoble our ſpirits and deck our heads; it will ſtrengthen our lawes with authority and juſtice, and ſharpen our ſwords againſt the faces of our enemies; it will make us <hi>a bleſsing and a praiſe above all the nations under Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
